<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bs on es Heavy Industries</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/b/categories/bs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bs on es Heavy Industries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 21:15:54 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/b/categories/bs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>So long and thanks for all the shoes...</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/b/2015/01/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-the-shoes.../</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 21:15:54 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/b/2015/01/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-the-shoes.../</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s kind of strange to start off a new blog with a goodbye post&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of living in the world of large corporations and the herd mindset I am going back to doing what I love: &lt;strong&gt;building shit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more operating in a culture where risk is looked down upon and the people who take those risks (or just suggest taking them) are typically not welcomed or are ignored. No more working in an environment where mediocrity is rewarded and innovation is stifled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead I&amp;rsquo;ll be moving to an environment where innovation is a first class citizen and is one of the keys to success. An environment where the majority of your day is not spent in meetings talking about building things but instead is actually &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spent building those things&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be going back to early in my career and joining, what I believe, is an awesome stealth mode start-up where I will be working with a small team as we build everything from the ground up. Not only do I get to work with really smart people who care about what they are building, but I get to help develop the right technology for the job instead of getting someone else&amp;rsquo;s old crap that was selected because the vendor took them out for drinks or something.&lt;br /&gt;
So hello &lt;a href=&#34;http://zachholman.com/talk/move-fast-break-nothing/&#34;&gt;move fast and try not to break things&lt;/a&gt; and goodbye &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groundhog_Day_%28film%29&#34;&gt;ground hog day&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ldquo;We don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of time on this earth! We weren&amp;rsquo;t meant to spend it this way! Human beings were not meant to sit in little cubicles staring at computer screens all day, filling out useless forms and listening to eight different bosses drone on about mission statements!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>