<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on es Heavy Industries</title>
    <link>http://esheavyindustries.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on es Heavy Industries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 13:02:40 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://esheavyindustries.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Have some extra cash? Help make your life easier</title>
      <link>http://esheavyindustries.com/2016/02/have-some-extra-cash-help-make-your-life-easier/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 13:02:40 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://esheavyindustries.com/2016/02/have-some-extra-cash-help-make-your-life-easier/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have some extra cash maybe you would consider donating some of it to one of the various open source projects that you likely use almost every single day? I know it is easy to forgot about where many of the things we use on a daily basis come from, but odds are that if you are reading this you probably use some kind of open source app.
Where would you be without &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openbsd.org/donations.html&#34;&gt;OpenSSH&lt;/a&gt; to securely connect to your servers?
I know I&amp;rsquo;d personally be fucked without &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haproxy.org/&#34;&gt;HAProxy&lt;/a&gt; doing the load balancing for many of the apps I&amp;rsquo;ve supported.
What about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apache.org/foundation/contributing.html&#34;&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt;? Sure it might not be the hot tech now but how many of you have used it as your HTTP server both at work or for your personal site?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on and on but the point I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make is that there are many (many!) tools that we use on a daily basis that someone (or a group of someones) are building, fixing and maintaining that make our lives easier.
Some of these have big corporate sponsors but many of them do not.
A lot of these people have other jobs they use to pay the bills and then work on their open source projects during their &amp;ldquo;off&amp;rdquo; time.
Some groups build products, others focus on your rights (take the &lt;a href=&#34;https://supporters.eff.org/donate/button&#34;&gt;EFF&lt;/a&gt; for example). Others, like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.torproject.org/donate/donate.html.en&#34;&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt; project, do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to make a list of some of the open source tools you use on a daily basis and consider donating either money or time to those projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>deb-simple, a no frills apt repository server</title>
      <link>http://esheavyindustries.com/2016/02/deb-simple-a-no-frills-apt-repository-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 01:46:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://esheavyindustries.com/2016/02/deb-simple-a-no-frills-apt-repository-server/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently needed an simple way to serve up debian packages via apt-get for our internal apps. Oddly enough finding something that fit our needs was a bit harder than I thought. We needed something that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supported multiple versions of the same package&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Didn&amp;rsquo;t care about signing or &amp;ldquo;changes&amp;rdquo; files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowed us to upload via an API or some type of incoming directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could handle multiple packages coming in at once without corrupting the repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was easy to setup/maintain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few services out there that fit our needs but they were not free so I took a shot at building an app to fit our use-case. The outcome was &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/esell/deb-simple&#34;&gt;deb-simple&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently it supports uploading packages via POST, deleting packages via DELETE and does a good job (I think) of making sure the repository listing doesn&amp;rsquo;t become corrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>