<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on es Heavy Industries</title>
    <link>http://esheavyindustries.com/b/categories/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on es Heavy Industries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 20:34:11 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://esheavyindustries.com/b/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazing Chaos aka Parenthood</title>
      <link>http://esheavyindustries.com/b/2015/02/amazing-chaos-aka-parenthood/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 20:34:11 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://esheavyindustries.com/b/2015/02/amazing-chaos-aka-parenthood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;this post stems from reading horrible news stories, multiple days in a row, about young children dieing because of parental neglect and/or abuse and wondering how someone could do something so awful&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The hardest job you&amp;rsquo;ll ever love&amp;rdquo; is a perfect phrase describing what parenting is to me. I have dealt with quite a wide range of things in my life and none of them even come close to the difficulty of the first 3 months with my son. Sure, everyone knows about the lack of sleep but what about the stress? You are now responsible for a living, breathing person that is 100% dependent on you for survival.
Oh yeah, this new person also has no real way of communicating with you what it is they actually need. If you are a &amp;ldquo;type a&amp;rdquo; person then you are in for even more of a ride.
Forget having any control or structure over anything. You can try, and you might get a few wins here-and-there, but overall you are in a world of constant change where things change by the hour so buckle up!
Did I mention there are no owners manuals either? Something as simple as how to give this new person you have a bath becomes rocket science that only adds to that stress you have building in you.
Now back to that sleep thing (ha!), all of this is happening while you are literally running on empty. It&amp;rsquo;s not only the fact that you are only sleeping a couple of hours a night but also that those hours are typically not in consecutive order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know how I currently spend my weekends? Sitting around with my wife watching our child learn, play, laugh and cry. That&amp;rsquo;s it. I literally will spend most weekends just sitting there on the floor watching him as he does what small children do (which is everything!) and I don&amp;rsquo;t regret it one bit, in fact there have been multiple times where I thought to myself &amp;ldquo;this is awesome&amp;rdquo;.
Sure there are times when I think it would be nice to be able to just go do something on a whim without any planning but those occasions are rare and quickly brushed aside when I see him and am filled with an overwhelming feeling of love.
The love that I have for him is something that cannot be described and can only be felt. It is something that I have never felt in all of my life.
&lt;br&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t end there though. &lt;br&gt;
The feeling of pride that comes over you when your child does something for the first time on their own is just incredible. If you could capture that feeling somehow and sell it you would be a billionaire. You are watching this child learn EVERYTHING right before your eyes.
This is not someone learning a new hobby or something, they are literally learning how to survive and become their own person.
Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a great feeling when you get a raise at work or when your team wins but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t even come close to seeing your child walk for the first time or the first time they call you &amp;ldquo;dada&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;mama&amp;rdquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s like the biggest team accomplishment ever as all of you have been putting in work to help reach this goal. Your child of course has been doing the majority of this work, surely falling and stumbling along the way, but has managed to overcome all of the obstacles and has now taken another step towards independence. The best part is that these moments are going to just keep coming as your child grows and gets older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are committed 100%, total dedication to this new human. Sure, there are &amp;ldquo;selfish&amp;rdquo; breaks where you step outside those lines for a bit. A night out with friends here, a large non-baby item purchase there, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t change your focus or your goals for your child. From here on out everything you do is for them.
&lt;br&gt;And I don&amp;rsquo;t mind it at all. &lt;br&gt;
For me being able to hopefully provide for my son whatever he needs or wants (within reason) is a great motivator and something I feel that I owe him. He has had such a drastic impact on my life that all I want to do is make sure he is happy. My hope is that his mother and I can raise him in such a fashion that if he ever has a child of his own, the foundation we established for him will allow him to raise a child in the same manner.
It has been quite the shift in mindset as now I am always thinking about what I will leave behind instead of what is going on right now. A few years ago I couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell you what was happening next week but now I have plans for 30 years from now and it&amp;rsquo;s all because of one tiny (currently) person.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So long and thanks for all the shoes...</title>
      <link>http://esheavyindustries.com/b/2015/01/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-the-shoes.../</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 21:15:54 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://esheavyindustries.com/b/2015/01/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-the-shoes.../</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s kind of strange to start off a new blog with a goodbye post&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of living in the world of large corporations and the herd mindset I am going back to doing what I love: &lt;strong&gt;building shit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more operating in a culture where risk is looked down upon and the people who take those risks (or just suggest taking them) are typically not welcomed or are ignored. No more working in an environment where mediocrity is rewarded and innovation is stifled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead I&amp;rsquo;ll be moving to an environment where innovation is a first class citizen and is one of the keys to success. An environment where the majority of your day is not spent in meetings talking about building things but instead is actually &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spent building those things&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be going back to early in my career and joining, what I believe, is an awesome stealth mode start-up where I will be working with a small team as we build everything from the ground up. Not only do I get to work with really smart people who care about what they are building, but I get to help develop the right technology for the job instead of getting someone else&amp;rsquo;s old crap that was selected because the vendor took them out for drinks or something.&lt;br /&gt;
So hello &lt;a href=&#34;http://zachholman.com/talk/move-fast-break-nothing/&#34;&gt;move fast and try not to break things&lt;/a&gt; and goodbye &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groundhog_Day_%28film%29&#34;&gt;ground hog day&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ldquo;We don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of time on this earth! We weren&amp;rsquo;t meant to spend it this way! Human beings were not meant to sit in little cubicles staring at computer screens all day, filling out useless forms and listening to eight different bosses drone on about mission statements!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>